Guide to the Edward Lasker Collection of Atlases and Maps, 1549-1926
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Edward Lasker Collection of Atlases and Maps
1549-1926
Lasker, Edward
1 cubic foot (3 boxes), 14 volumes
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Collection of atlases and maps depicting the globe, North and South America, the West Indies, Germany, Wales, and regions of the United States from the 16th to 19th centuries.
Scope and Content Note
Collection of atlases and maps depicting the globe, North and South America, the West Indies, and regions of Europe and the United States from the 16th to 19th centuries.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Series I. Atlases, [1572]-1926; and Series II. Maps, 1549-1864.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Atlas Collection
Breed Collection of Maps, Documents, and Prints
Richmond John Rathbone Collection of Rare Maps
Vassar College Archives Maps Collection
Subject Headings
Names:
Blaeu, Joan, 1596-1673; Blaeu, Willem Janszoon, 1571-1638; Bodenehr, Gabriel, active 17th century-18th century; Bowen, Emanuel, 1693 or 1694-1767; Faden, William, 1749-1836; Fry, Joshua, approximately 1700-1754; Green, John, -1757; Grenet, abbé, 1750-; Homann, Johann Baptist, 1663-1724; Hubbard, William, 1621 or 1622-1704; Humphreys, Arthur L. (Arthur Lee), 1865-1946; L'Isle, Guillaume de, 1675-1726; Jansson, Jan, 1588-1664; Jefferys, Thomas, -1771; Kitchin, Thomas, 1719-1784; Lotter, Tobias Conrad, 1717-1777; Lowitz, G. M. (George Moritz), 1722-1774; Manuel, Hans Rudolf, 1525-1571; Mercator, Gerhard, 1512-1594; Ortelius, Abraham, 1527-1598; Popple, Henry, -1743; Seutter, Matthäus, 1678-1757; Wit, Frederik de, 1629 or 1630-1706; Zürner, Adam Friedrich, 1679-1742
Places:
Germany--Maps; New England--Maps; New York (State)--Maps; North America--Maps; South America--Maps; United States--Maps; West Indies--Maps
Document Types:
Atlases; Maps
VCL Categories:
Maps
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, September 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Loula Lasker (VC 1909), 1937.
Series List
- Series I. Atlases, [1572]-1926
  Arranged alphabetically by creator or title.
- Series II. Maps, 1549-1864
  Arranged according to original order of portfolios.
Container List
- Series I. Atlases, [1572]-1926
  - "Atlas moderne: ou Collection de cartes sur toutes les parties du globe terrestre / par plusieurs auteurs; avec approbation & privilege du roy," Paris: Lattre & Delalain, 1762-1773 (Folio G1015 .A85 1762)
  - Blaeu, Willem Jansz (1571-1638), "Theatrum orbis terrarum, sive Atlas novus: in quo tabulae et descriptiones omnium regionum," Amsterdami: Apud Iohannem Guiljelmi F. Blaeu, [1644]; [Vol. 1] (Folio G1015 .B53 1644)
  - Blaeu, Willem Jansz (1571-1638), "Guil. et Ioannis Blaeu theatrum orbis terrarum, sive Atlas novus. Pars secunda," Amsterdami: Apud Iohannem Guiljelmi F. Blaeu, [1645]; [Vol. 2] (Folio G1015 .B53 1645)
  - [A collection of maps, most issued by Johann Baptist Homann or his heirs], [S.l.]: [s.n.], [1789?] (Folio G1015 .H66 1789)
  - Faden, William, "[Atlas with maps colored according to the Definitive Treaty of Peace, 1815]," [London]: [W. Faden ... [and 10 others in 4 other places], 1780-1838 (Folio G1019 .F33 1780)
  - Grenet, abbé (1750-), "Compendio di geografia antica e moderna formato sulle carte più esatte: opera utilisima per apprendere l'una e l'altra geografia…," Venezia: presso Andrea Santini, 1794 (Folio G1015 .G74 1794)
  - Humphreys, Arthur Lee (1865-1946), "Old decorative maps and charts. With illustrations from engravings in the Macpherson collection, and a catalogue of the atlases, etc., in the collection by Henry Stevens," London: Halton and T. Smith, ltd., N.Y.: Minton, Balch & Co., 1926 (Folio G1025 .H8 1926)
  - Jefferys, Thomas (-1771), "The American atlas, or, A geographical description of the whole continent of America; wherein are delineated at large, its several regions, countries, states, and islands; and chiefly the British colonies, composed from numerous surveys...," London: R. Sayer and Bennett, 1778 (Folio G1100 .J44 1778)
  - Kitchin, Thomas (1719-1784), "A general atlas, describing the whole universe: being a complete collection of the most approved maps extant; corrected with the greatest care, and augmented from the latest discoveries…," London: Printed for Robert Sayer, [1788?] (Folio G1015 .K58 1788)
  - Mercator, Gerhard (1512-1594), "Atlas minor / Gerardi Mercatoris; à I. Hondio plurimis aeneis tabulis auctus et illustratus: denuo recognit additisque novis delineationibus emendatis," Amsterodami: Ex officina Ioannis Ianssoni, 1634 (G1007 1634)
  - Ortelius, Abraham (1527-1598), "Nomenclator Ptolemaicus: omnia locorum vocabula, quae in tota Ptolemaei Geographia occurrunt, continens ad fidem Graeci codicis purgatus, & in ordinem non minus vtilem quàm elegantem digestus," Antuerpiae: Typis Roberti Bruneau, 1607 (Folio G1006 .T53 1612)
  - Ortelius, Abraham (1527-1598), "[Theatro del mondo di Abrahamo Ortelio: da lui poco inanzi la sua morte riueduto, & di tauole nuoue, et commenti adorno, & arricchito, con la vita dell'autore / traslato in lingua toscana dal sigr. Filippo Pigafetta]," [In Anversa]: [si vende nella libraria Plantiniana], [1612] (Folio G1006 .T53 1612)
  - Ortelius, Abraham (1527-1598), "[Theatrum oder Schawplatz des Erdbodems warin die Landttafell der gantzen Weldt: mit sambt aine der selben kurtze Erklarung zu sehen ist / durch Abrahaumum Ortelium]," [Antorff]: [Gielis von Diest], [1572] (Folio G1006 .T53 1572)
  - Popple, Henry (-1743), "A map of the British Empire in America: with the French and Spanish settlements adjacent thereto," [London]: [Sold by S. Harding and W.H. Toms], [1733] (Folio G1106.F3 P67 1733)
  - Wit, Frederik de (1629 or 1630-1706), "Atlas," Tot Amsterdam: Bij Frederick de Wit in de Calverstreat bij den dam inde Witte Paskaert, 1688 (Folio G1015 .W58 1688)
- Series II. Maps, 1549-1864
  - Portfolio I (North America and the United States)
    - [North America] Jansson, Jan (d. 1666), "Nova Belgica et Anglia Nova,", circa 1641 (Portfolio I, Item no. 1)
    - [North America] Lotter, Tobias Conrad (1717-1777), "Becens edita totius Novi Belgii…,", circa 1740 (Portfolio I, Item no. 2)
    - [North America] "A new and accurate map of the English Empire in America…,", circa 1755 (Portfolio I, Item no. 3)
    - [North America] Seutter, Matthew (1678-1756), "Mappa geographica regionem Mexicanan et Floridam, terrasque adjacentes…,", circa 1740 (Portfolio I, Item no. 4)
    - [New England] Hubbard, William (1621-1704), "A map of New-England, being the first that ever was here cut…,", 1677 (Portfolio I, Item no. 5)
    - [New England] Kitchin, Thomas (1718-1784), "A map of New England, and Nova Scotia; with part of New York, Canada, and New Britain…,", 1758 (Portfolio I, Item no. 6)
    - [New England] Homann, Johann Baptist (1663-1724), "Nova Anglia Septentrionali Americae...,", circa 1720 (Portfolio I, Item no. 7)
    - [New England] Green, John (1729?-1757?), "A map of the most inhabited part of New England…,", 1776 (Portfolio I, Item no. 8)
    - [Connecticut] Kitchin, Thomas (1718-1784), "A map of the colonies of Connecticut and Rhode Island…,", 1758 (Portfolio I, Item no. 9)
    - [New York (State)] "The country between Crown Point and Albany, being the great pass from the English to the French settlements in North America,", 1758 (Portfolio I, Item no. 10)
    - [New York (City)] Bittner, Franklin, "A plan of the city of New York in the yeare 1664…," (Portfolio I, Item no. 11)
    - [New York (City)] Lyne, James, "A plan of the city of New York from an actual survey…,", 1728; [Reproduction from 1926] (Portfolio I, Item no. 12)
    - [Virginia] Fry, Joshua (1700?-1754), "A map of the most inhabited part of Virginia containing the whole province of Maryland with part of Pensilvania, New Jersey and North Carolina…,", 1775 (Portfolio I, Item no. 13)
    - [Texas] "A New map of Texas, Oregon and California with the regions adjoining…,", 1846 (Portfolio I, Item no. 14)
    - [U.S., Western] "Colton's map of the Pacific states…,", 1864 (Portfolio I, Item no. 15)
    - [St. Lawrence River] Kitchin, Thomas (1718-1784), "A new chart of the river St. Lawrence from the island of Anticosti to Lake Ontario,", 1759 (Portfolio I, Item no. 16)
  - Portfolio II (North and South America, West Indies)
    - [America] Vaughan, Robert (engraver), "Americae nova descriptio,", 1663 (Portfolio II, Item no. 1)
    - [America] "The western hemisphere, taken from an English world map or atlas,", [circa 1670?] (Portfolio II, Item no. 2)
    - [America] Wit, Frederik de (1629 or 1630-1706), "Novissima et accuratissima totius Americae descriptio,", circa 1695 (Portfolio II, Item no. 3)
    - [America] Homann, Johann Baptist (1663-1724), "Totius Americae Septentrionalis et Meridionalis novissima representatio…,", circa 1720 (Portfolio II, Item no. 4)
    - [America] Homann, Johann Baptist (1663-1724), "Totius Americae Septentrionalis et Meridionalis novissima representatio…,", circa 1730 (Portfolio II, Item no. 5)
    - [America] Seutter, Matthew (1678-1756), "Novus orbis sive America Meridionalis et Septentrionalis…,", circa 1740 (Portfolio II, Item no. 6)
    - [America] Boehm, August Gottlob (1719-1797), "Americae mappa generalis…,", 1746 (Portfolio II, Item no. 7)
    - [West Indies] Homann heirs, "Dominia Anglorum in praecipuis insulis Americae…,", circa 1759 (Portfolio II, Item no. 8)
    - [Jamaica] "A new map of the island of Jamaica...,", 18th century (Portfolio II, Item no. 9)
    - [Cuba] "A new chart of the seas, surrounding the island of Cuba…,", 1762 (Portfolio II, Item no. 10)
    - [Martinique] Seutter, Matthew (1678-1756), "Representation la plus nouvelle et exacte de l'ile Martinique…,", circa 1740 (Portfolio II, Item no. 11)
    - [South America] Delisle, Guillaume (1675-1726), "L'Amerique meridionale…,", circa 1720 (Portfolio II, Item no. 12)
  - Portfolio III (Europe and the World)
    - [World] Zuerner, Adam Friedrich (1630-1742), "Planisphaerium terrestre cum utroque coelesti hemisphaerio…,", circa 1712 (Portfolio III, Item no. 1)
    - [World] Lowitz, George Maurice (1722-1774), "Planiglobii terrestris mappa universalis…,", 1746 (Portfolio III, Item no. 2)
    - [World] Bowen, Emanuel (d. 1767), "An accurate map of the world…,", circa 1750 (Portfolio III, Item no. 3)
    - [Wales, Pembrokeshire] Blaeu, Joan (1596-1673), "Penbrochia comitatus et comitatus Caermaridunum…,", circa 1662 (Portfolio III, Item no. 4)
    - [Germany, Baden (province)] Weimar - Geographisches institut, "Theil von Baden… Partis de Baade,", [1808?] (Portfolio III, Item no. 5)
    - [Germany, Breisgau] Seutter, Matthew (1678-1756), "Accurata delinaeatio Brisgoviae…,", circa 1740 (Portfolio III, Item no. 6)
    - [Germany, Freiburg im Breisgau] Bodenehr, Gabriel (1664-1758), "Freiburg im Brisgow,", circa 1705 (Portfolio III, Item no. 7)
    - [Germany, Freiburg im Breisgau] Deutsch, Hans Rudolf Manuel (1525-1571), "Friburg im Brisgew,", 1549 (Portfolio III, Item no. 8)
    - [Germany, Freiburg im Breisgau] Deutsch, Hans Rudolf Manuel (1525-1571), "Friburg im Brisgew,", 1549 (Portfolio III, Item no. 9)
    - [Germany, Freiburg im Breisgau] "Die statt Freyburg im Breysgaw,", [1646?] (Portfolio III, Item no. 10)
    - [Germany, Heidelberg] "Heidelberga…,", [1576?] (Portfolio III, Item no. 11)